找到他 杀了他
Find him, kill him.
能让他回心转意不是要好得多?
How much better if we were to win him back?
他带着人手穿越荒漠来杀我
He dragged men across the desert to kill me.
大帝已经启程离开了
Our emperor has departed,
但他给耶路撒冷留了一份大礼
but he has left a present for Jerusalem.
大帝的一座雕像
A statue of his likeness.
他要求放在神殿里
Which he commands to be placed in the temple itself.
我们说的可是神殿的毁灭!
This is about the destruction of the temple!
欢迎扫罗成为我们信基督的兄弟
We welcome Saul as our brother in Christ.
你们都疯了
You've all lost your minds.
西门
Simon.
- 这是我的错  - 不要去 扫罗
- This is my fault.  - No, Saul.
我必须要弥补
I have to make it right.
我听说如果你想见某人
I've heard that if you want to meet certain people,
就来这里
then this is the place to come.
罗马的敌人?
Enemies of Rome?
那说吧
So, talk.
- 他在这里  - 找到他
- He's here.  - Find him.
嗷!
Oh!
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第10集
加利利
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调: 影子
翻译: 飘飘行天下 AU薇 舒大卷子
耶稣
Jesus.
翻译: 喵喵 猫呗 鸟生鱼汤 波特妹子
校对: 飘飘行天下 影子
耶稣
Jesus.
至于神 他的道是完全的
As for God, his way is perfect.
耶和华的话是炼净的
The word of the Lord is flawless.
耶稣 你在做什么?
Jesus. What are you doing?
我们到处找你
We've been looking everywhere.
难道你不知道我会在父的家里?
Didn't you know I would be in my father's house?
你将永远知道去哪里找我 雅各
You will always know where to find me, James.
扫罗就是这样的人
That's how he is. That's Saul.
你什么话也不能对他说
You can't tell him anything.
没错 我们早该阻止他
No, we should have stopped him.
我早该如此
I should have.
他们会乱石砸死他 是吗?
They'll stone him, won't they?
也许大祭司会饶他一命
Maybe the high priest will be lenient.
没可能 该亚法没这么宽宏大量
Not a chance. Not Caiaphas.
你们觉得西门也被抓了吗?
Do you think they've got Simon, too?
不然他还能在哪?
Where else would he be?
他们不会把两个人都处死吧 会吗?
They won't kill them both, will they?
不会的
No.
因为我会阻止他们
Because I won't let them.
什么意思?
What do you mean?
我要去神殿
I will go to the temple,
求他们放人
and I will beg for their release.
走!
Move!
欢迎回来 扫罗
Welcome back, Saul.
看看这些人因信仰而团结在一起
Look at all these people united in their faith.
而你却不在其中
And then there's you.
我明白你的愤怒
I understand your anger.
你来找我
You came to me.
你求我让你去
You begged me to let you
抓捕那些渎神者 保卫神殿
attack these blasphemers and defend the temple.
我想引你注意
I wanted to impress you.
但我现在已经明白了真相
But now I understand the truth.
你的老师... 迦玛列...
What would your teacher... Gamaliel...
他会怎么看你的新觉悟?
make of your new understanding?
你想让我做什么?
What do you want from me?
你现在有机会
You have a chance right now
向神忏悔你的罪恶返回正道
to confess to your sins before God and turn back.
回来吧 扫罗
Come back, Saul.
回归神殿
Come back to the temple.
不要背弃爱你的人
Do not betray those who love you.
你正身处宇宙的中心
You're here in the center of universe.
你怎么能离开? 怎能脱离神?
How can you leave? Cut yourself off from God?
你的信仰就在这里
This is your faith here, right here.
我想宽恕你
I want to forgive you.
他们都心满意足
They all look so content.
当然了 他们身处家园
Of course they do. They're home.
这里确实感觉像家园
It does feel like home.
但其实并不是
But it isn't.
你也不能宽恕我
And you cannot forgive me.
只有耶稣才能这么做
Only Jesus can do that.
对
Yes.
太好了 大比大
Very good, Tabitha.
好极了
Excellent.
我错过了什么?
What have I missed?
跟我讲讲
Tell me.
我们刚刚在说洗衣缝补还有...
We've been talking about washing and sewing and...
其他什么都没说
And nothing else whatsoever.
肯定说了
No, you haven't.
跟我讲讲针的故事
Tell me about the needle.
耶稣说"骆驼穿过...
Jesus said, "it is easier for..."
"骆驼穿过针的眼
"it's easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle
比财主进神的国
than it is for a rich man
还容易呢"
to enter the kingdom of heaven."
那财主婆呢?
And what about a rich woman?
现在重复你刚说的话
Now. Say that again.
以赛亚的预言已经应验
Isaiah's prophecy has been completed.
耶稣是我们的弥赛亚
Jesus is our Messiah.
他从死里复活
He rose from the dead,
而我奉他的名重生
and I have been born again in his name.
我已经悔改
I have repented.
他也已饶恕我
And he has forgiven me.
我的罪永远被洗去了
And my sins are forever washed away.
所以在我看来已... 你无需
So, it seems to me that there is... no need
无止境地寻求圣洁的仪式
for your endless search for ritual purity,
你的浸礼池 你那套神殿的繁文缛节都不需要
nor your mikvahs, nor any of your temple customs.
不需要?
No need?
对神殿来说不需要
No need for the temple.
对你也不需要
No need for you.
你这是怎么了?
What happened to you?
你这是怎么了?!
What happened to you?!
39下鞭刑会治好你的疯病吗?
Would 39 lashes cure your madness?
在监狱里待一个月如何?
How about a month in a cell?
直到你恢复理智
Till you see sense.
我可以把你丢在里面日渐衰弱
I could leave you there to waste away,
直到你被彻底遗忘
until you're completely forgotten.
我相信一定会有其他方案
I'm sure there must be another plan
- 不会牺牲掉你  - 躲得够久了
- that doesn't involve you dying.  - Enough hiding.
是啊 但如果他也把你投进监狱怎么办?
Yeah, but what if he throws you in jail, too?
那你就按耶稣教我们的去宣讲传道
Then you'll preach and spread the word as Jesus taught us.
嗯 好吧 我们会试试的
Well, yeah, all right. We'll try.
但如果你走了 谁来领导我们呢?
But if you're gone, who's gonna lead us?
因为我觉得多马无法胜任
'Cause I don't think Thomas can cope.
雅各
James.
是雅各!
It's James!
到那时他已经失踪三天了
By this time, he'd been missing for three days.
他的母亲忧心忡忡
His mother was beside herself with worry.
但他竟然在神殿里
But there he was, in the temple,
和一群祭司争吵辩论
debating and arguing with the priests
好像那是世上再自然不过的事
as though it was the most natural thing in the world.
这就是我的梦
I had that dream.
于是我就知道我必须和你们待在这里
And I knew then that I had to be here with you.
我很想你
I've missed you.
他小时候是什么样的?
What was he like? As a boy.
小的时候我们都在一起玩
We all used to play together as children.
他和我们其他人并无二致
He was just like the rest of us.
之后你... 你就开始注意到一些区别
But then you... you'd start to notice things.
比如他的... 与年龄不符的冷静和智慧
Like his... his calmness, his wisdom,
还有他的善良
even when he was young, his kindness.
他的眼中闪烁着... 某种东西
He had something... something in his eyes.
我爱他
I loved him.
我非常爱他
I loved him very much.
但那都过去了
But that was then.
现在我想听听你们怎么样了
Now I want to hear about you.
我知道你们都曾被捕入狱
I understand you've all been imprisoned.
有些人还入狱两次
Some of us twice.
但是我相信你们仍然...
And yet, still, you continue...
取得了重大的进展
making great strides, I'm sure.
怎么了?
Well, what is it?
我们昨天折损了两名兄弟
We lost two brothers yesterday.
有个新的信徒扫罗被神殿守卫抓了
A new believer, Saul, was seized by the temple guards,
还有西门... 他昨晚没回来
and Simon... he didn't come back last night.
我必须到神殿走一趟
I have to go to the temple.
去见大祭司长吗?
To see the high priest?
他可关押过你两次
Who has imprisoned you twice.
我们也这么跟他说了
We've been trying to tell him.
我去怎样?
What if I went?
谢谢你 但这是我的责任
Thank you, but it is my burden.
那让我为他们求求情
Well, let me plead for them.
你不了解他
You do not know him.
他会看出你眼底的害怕
He will see the fear in your eyes.
恕我自负 但我也是一个拉比
And, forgive my pride, but I'm also a rabbi.
他总要卖我个面子吧
That should count in our favor.
我已经让你们独自承受这一切太久了
I have left you here to suffer alone for too long.
让我帮帮你们吧
Let me help you.
你们来此有何贵干?
What is your business here?
有何贵干!
Your business!
他听不懂你说话
He does not understand you.
你是?
And you are?
埃塞俄比亚女王的银库总管
Chief treasurer to the queen of Ethiopia.
- 埃塞俄比亚?  - 没事的 百夫长
- Ethiopia?  - It's all right, centurion.
我们把武器留在城门了
We left our weapons at the city gates.
真的吗?
Really?
给我彻底搜
Search it. Every inch.
神圣的主 我没有听进
Blessed Lord, I have shut my ears
你的教训
to your teachings
也忽视了你的诫命
and ignored your commandments.
我无视他人的苦难
I have closed my eyes to the suffering of others.
尽管我不配
Though I am unworthy,
仍请求你的饶恕 仁慈的神 我发誓....
I ask your forgiveness, merciful God, and pledge...
不
No.
我刚刚看到扫罗了
I have just seen Saul.
我让他走的
I let him go.
他是一个疯子
He's a madman.
他所说的话会让他送命
His words will get him killed.
他是个无名小卒
He's nothing.
- 你不能这么做  - 已经结束了
- You can't do this.  - It's done.
你在示弱
And now you look weak.
让大家知道这只是... 赎罪日
Let the people know it was an act of... forgiveness
前夜的饶恕
on the Eve of Yom Kippur.
但是在其他任何时候....
But at any other time...
我已经说过了!
I have spoken!
它就要来了... 不知道还有一天还是一周
It's coming... in a day, in a week, I don't know,
但是那可憎之物即将到此...
but soon the abomination will be here...
一座将掀起血雨腥风的雕像
A statue that heralds eternal war.
你难道不懂我们需要联合每一个犹太人
Do you not see that we need to unite every Jew,
每一个小教派和异教团体
every tiny sect and cult
带领他们协力抗击这个庞然大怪?
and bring them all together to fight this monstrosity?
我懂了
Oh, I see.
这是在玩政治 是吗?
This is politics, is it?
一边是罗马的意志和它激发的恐惧
There is the will of Rome, the fear it inspires.
一边是我们
And there is us.
我们必须让他们的爱戴多于害怕
We must make them love more than fear,
不然我们都得死
or we will all die.
扫罗说的每一句话...
Every word that Saul speaks...
都是你声名的污点
is a stain upon your reputation.
你没听到我刚刚的话吗?
Did you not hear what I just said?
你没听到我的话吗?
Did you not just hear me?
你是耶路撒冷神殿的大祭司
You are the high priest of the temple of Jerusalem.
你什么时候才有大祭司的样子?
When will you act like it?
我有
I do.
每一天
Every day.
你只是太盲目了所以看不到
You're simply too blind to see it.
对不起 我昏头了
I'm sorry. I lost my head.
我们担心坏了 你去哪儿了?
We were worried. Where did you go?
在一个客栈 我喝了几杯
There's an inn. I had a few drinks.
然后又喝了几杯
Then a few more.
然后呢?
And then?
我醒过来发现我在一个马槽
And then I woke up in a horse trough.
见到你真高兴
We're so glad to see you.
回来的感觉太好了
It's good to be back.
没有什么好担心的 不要担心我
There's nothing to worry about. Not with me.
什么事也没有
Nothing at all.
他身上没发现武器?
And you found no weapons on him?
没有
None.
祭品和所有的篮子也查了吗?
And you checked the sacrifices, all the baskets?
一无所获
There was nothing.
可能他真的只是来神殿礼拜的
Maybe he really has come to visit the temple.
明天是他们的圣日 不是吗?
It's one of their holy days tomorrow, isn't it?
他是一个埃塞俄比亚人 克劳迪娅
The man's an Ethiopian, Claudia.
全世界都有人来耶路撒冷朝拜
People come from all over the world to visit Jerusalem.
你知道他对自己做了什么
Do you know what he'd have done to himself
才能成为女王的银库总管
to become the queen's treasurer
才能永远侍其左右?
and to assure everlasting devotion?
和以前比他只剩半个人了
He's half the man he used to be.
他知道雕像的事吗?
Does he know about the statue?
我没有...
I didn't...
你没问 当然 你不能问
You didn't ask. Of course, you couldn't.
我想见他
I want to see him.
面对面
Face to face.
请他来晚宴
A dinner invitation.
还有让希律和他妻子也来 这样就显得不那么...
And get Herod and his wife along so it seems less...
扎眼?
Obvious?
是的
Hm. Yes.
你告诉这个埃塞俄比亚太监
You tell this Ethiopian eunuch
我们很荣幸款待
that we would be honored to entertain
贵宾光临我们的城市
such an important visitor in our city.
你想要什么?
What do you want?
我需要一些东西
I need something.
你可以联系到人
You have contacts.
我只是个做首饰的
I just make jewelry.
我深表怀疑
Oh, I doubt that.
你走吧 我帮不了你
You should go. I can't help you.
我不会走的
I will not be dismissed.
出去
Get out.
你怎么看我并不重要
It doesn't matter what you think of me.
我要见你那伙人
I need to see your people.
要是他们知道你让他们失去
And they will not be happy when they discover
见我的机会 还有我提出的条件
you've denied them the chance to see me
肯定会不高兴的
and all that I can offer.
你要什么"东西"?
What is this "something"?
等见到他们我自然会说
I'll tell them when I see them.
你要么告诉我 要么就没有然后了
You'll tell me, or you'll get no further.
我想要一个人死
I want a man killed.
扫罗! 你究竟怎么了?
Saul! How on earth?
他们打你了吗?
Did they beat you?
没有
No.
那是雅各让他们放人的?
So James got you released?
雅各是谁? 他...
Who's James? He...
你就平白无故被放了?
You were just freed?
我不知道
I don't know.
我和大祭司谈了话 然后他就把我放了
I talked to the high priest, and... he just released me.
哼 好不可思议
Well, isn't that unbelievably lucky.
西门
Simon.
我们都曾被打 被捕 下狱...被扔石头
We were all beaten, arrested, imprisoned... or stoned.
而这个人就这样被放了?
And this man just walks free?
你到底想要指控我什么?
What are you accusing me of, exactly?
结束了
Well, it's over.
我自由了
I'm free.
我叫雅各 来自拿撒勒
My name is James... from Nazareth.
我追随耶稣
I follow Jesus.
你来神殿所为何事?
What brings you to the temple?
赎罪日将至 我们都要饶恕别人
We must all forgive as we approach the day of atonement,
不对吗?
isn't that right?
我应该饶恕你吗?
Should I forgive you?
我今天见到了我的兄弟
I met with my brothers today.
我必须假装我没受他们忧虑悲痛的影响
I had to pretend I was immune to their worries and grief,
假装比实际更强大
that I was so much stronger than I really am
都因为你
because of you.
你算什么大祭司 竟让他们这般恐惧?
What kind of a high priest are you to instill such fear?
我必须捍卫信仰
I must defend the faith.
那你做得太好了
Well, you do it too well.
我到这里要求释放我的两个兄弟...
I am here to ask for the release of two of my brothers...
大数人扫罗和迦百农人西门
Saul of Tarsus and Simon of Capernaum.
我帮不了你
I cannot help you.
西门从没来过这 而扫罗早就被放走了
Simon was never here, and Saul walked free earlier.
他们是怎么跟你说的?
What stories have they been telling you?
我们不是敌人 雅各
We aren't enemies, James.
我们都跪在神前祈求其赐福于我们
We both kneel before God and pray for his blessing.
若果真如此 那就不要再迫害我们
If this is true, stop persecuting us.
好吧 我知道为什么他们派你来了
Yes, I see why they sent you.
跟我来
Come.
我许诺予你们一个圣所怎么样?
What if I promised you sanctuary?
圣所?
Sanctuary?
可以安心祷告的地方 不再有迫害
A safe place to pray, an end to persecution.
与神殿讲和的机会
A chance to make peace with the temple.
为什么?
Why?
如你所言赎罪日将至
Well, as you say, it's nearly Yom Kippur.
还有别的原因吗?
Why else?
去和你的朋友们商量商量
Go talk to your friends.
让他们考虑一下我的提议
Let them consider my offer.
如果他们尊重神殿也能在这里祷告
If they respect the temple, then they may pray here.
但是扫罗除外
But not Saul.
扫罗?
Saul?
这里欢迎你们来
You are welcome here.
我想要团结我们的民族 但是他除外
I'm keen to unite our nation, but not him.
他做了什么?
What has he done?
显然你不了解他
You clearly don't know him.
日久见人心
You'll see.
感谢您在此接见我
Thank you for your kindness in meeting me here.
这是埃塞俄比亚女王
From the queen of Ethiopia,
作为虔诚信徒的一点心意
and... from a humble believer.
多谢贵国的慷慨馈赠
Thank you for your wonderful generosity.
请接受我们的回礼
Please accept in return
这幅经文出自我们的先知以赛亚
these writings by our prophet Isaiah.
我会郑重珍视
I will treasure these words.
我们祷告吧?
Shall we pray?
那是再好不过了
Prayer would be wonderful.
你今晚到犹太省巡抚宫殿用膳
You will dine today at the palace of the governor of Judea.
这里还轮不到你
It is not your place
在我的神殿里对贵宾呼来喝去
to give orders to an honored guest in my temple.
没关系
It is fine.
我们已经习惯了罗马人的礼节
We are used to the Roman etiquette.
我会去的
As you wish.
很抱歉如此对你
I apologize for that.
尤其你还是大祭司的夫人
Especially when it involves the wife of the high priest.
但是我们必须谨慎行事
But we must be careful.
你在询问杀人的事
You have been asking about murder.
一个渎神者 也是这个国家的敌人
A blasphemer and an enemy of the state.
那就处死他
So remove him.
你丈夫有这个权利
Your husband has the power.
我明白了
The high priest is willing
大祭司放了这异教徒一条活路
to let this heretic live, I take it.
但你不愿意
But not you.
他对我们所有人都是个威胁
He's a danger to us all.
对我也是?
To me?
我很怀疑
I doubt that.
这个人是谁?
Who is this man?
大数人扫罗
Saul of Tarsus.
最近他加入了拿撒勒人的异教
He recently joined the cult of the Nazarenes.
我们和拿撒勒人并无恩怨
We have no quarrel with the Nazarenes.
那好啊 就让那些亵渎神的人逍遥自在
Oh, well, let those who mock God walk in peace.
我不知道你的信仰竟松懈到如此地步了
I had no idea how lax your convictions had become.
我奉劝你不要质疑我的信仰
I would not advise you to question my faith.
不要在这
Not here.
不要一个人
Not alone.
更不要在你蓄意和罗马人勾结的时候
And not when you so willfully share your sheets with Rome.
而且你可以为我做什么?
And what will you do for me?
你想要什么?
What do you want?
你丈夫对大帝的雕像是怎样打算的?
What are your husband's plans for the emperor's statue?
是 我都知道了
Yes, I know all about it.
他会怎么做?
What will he do?
我不确定
I'm not sure.
我们还以为他对你言听计从呢
We all assumed he did whatever you told him.
我只是他的妻子
I'm just his wife.
我欣赏你的回答
I like your answer.
我喜欢你这种巧妙逃避责任的方法
I like the way you swerve to avoid responsibility,
但你愚弄不了任何人
but you fool no one.
亲爱的利亚 我想要从你这得到的是鲜血
What I want from you, dear Leah, is blood.
我想要一千罗马人的血
I want the blood of a thousand Romans,
而你要让你的丈夫和神殿
and you will influence your husband and the temple
将这些鲜血通通给我
to give it to me.
怎么做?
How?
我需要你时 你就知道怎么做了
When I need you, you'll know.
不行 不行 不行
No. No. No.
我有件新的长袍
I had a new gown.
丝绸面料的
A silk one.
大比大现在应该做好了
Tabitha should have finished it by now.
他还没到吧?
He's not here yet, is he?
没 你还有时间 一切顺利吗?
No, you have time. Is everything all right?
我的裁缝还没做好我的衣裳
My seamstress has not completed her work.
我有裁缝 跟我来
We have seamstresses. Follow me.
真为你感到高兴
I'm so happy for you.
我会带你去使徒那接受洗礼
I'll take you to the apostles and have you baptized.
太好了
It's wonderful.
你会感觉到自己的存在... 如此鲜活
You will feel alive... so alive,
从未有过的感觉
like you've never felt before.
谢谢你
Thank you.
约亚拿 谢谢你指引我走向耶稣
Thank you, Joanna, for leading me to Jesus.
在发生了那么多事之后
You tried to lure my other servants to Jesus
你还想引诱其他仆人信仰耶稣?
after everything that has happened?
这都是我的错
This is my fault.
我等会再和你算账
And I will deal with you later.
现在我们要准备招待贵宾
Right now we have an important guest to prepare for.
你怎么能这样?
How could you?
希罗底 她还是个孩子
Herodias, she's a child.
这显然是我的仆人的错
This is clearly the fault of my own servant,
我会和她算账
and I will deal with her.
你想教训你的仆人你去教训便是
You may punish your servant as you wish,
但是这些女孩是我手下的
but these girls, they belong to me.
你们俩都从我的家仆中除名了
You are both banished from my household
明早前就走
and will be gone by morning.
现在快滚吧!
Now get out!
听着 我知道他对你们都做了什么
Look, I know what he has done to you all.
但是感觉他很诚恳
But it felt genuine.
我们该怎么做?
What do we have to do?
只要尊重神殿就好
Just respect the temple.
- 就这样?  - 是的
- And that's all?  - Yes.
其它的容后再论
We can negotiate the rest.
我们可以大胆出门
We could go outside without fear.
我们可以庆祝节日和圣日
We could celebrate festivals and holy days.
我们为什么需要神殿?
Why do we need the temple?
当然我们需要安全感
Of course we want to feel safe.
我不怀疑这一点 但是...
I don't dispute that, but...
既然耶稣已经复活 为什么还要去那?
now that Jesus has risen, why bother to go there?
他就在这... 在我们内心 伴我们左右
He is here... in us, with us.
所以为什么要去?
So why?
所以神殿是...?
So, the temple is...?
旧法的一部分 而旧法已然结束
Part of the old law, which is now been completed.
我们仍是犹太人 扫罗
We are still Jews, Saul.
神殿是我们生活的重要部分
The temple is an important part of our lives.
我们还有福音要宣讲 雅各
We have message to preach, James.
但是和那一堆石头没有关系
But it has nothing to do with that pile of stones.
你就这么舍弃它了?
You would just abandon it?
我只想出去宣扬基督的言语
I just want to go out and spread the word of Christ.
神殿再无关联
The temple is no longer relevant.
这不难理解
It's not that difficult to understand.
那一定是我傻了
I must be stupid, then.
西门
Simon.
这个人 这个陌生人
We have this man, this stranger,
一分钟前还想要我们都死光
who one minute wants us all dead.
又来一遍吗 彼得?
All this again, Peter?
然后不知怎地就毫发无损地
And then somehow gets released by the high priest
被大祭司释放
without a scratch on him.
现在我不知道他在干什么
Now I don't know what he's doing.
你不知道
No, you don't,
所以等你知道了再开口
so you should be quiet until you do.
我不相信你们有谁信任他
I can't believe any of you trust him.
西门
Simon.
别叫我
No.
西门!
Simon!
趁着还能喝酒 要来点吗?
Some wine, while you can?
等日落你们就要开始斋戒了
Your fast begins at sunset, I believe.
我很惊讶你会注意这些事
I'm surprised you pay attention to such matters.
巡抚参与到犹太事务中来
Well, the governor makes a point
表明了他的重视
of getting involved in Jewish affairs.
肯定有些你们不常见的习俗我没遵守
I certainly won't be following your obscure customs.
得恕我无礼
You'll have to forgive me.
我们在赎罪日会去宽恕
On Yom Kippur, we try to forgive
并且和所有敌人和解
and make peace with all our enemies.
我们是敌人吗?
Are we enemies?
我以为这里的都是朋友
I thought we were all friends here.
不对吗 希律?
Isn't that right, Herod?
是的 我们确实相互礼貌
It's true. We do manage a certain civility.
尽管你们罗马人习惯
Although, you Romans have a habit
上哪都要树敌
of making enemies wherever you go.
在罗马统治下民族团结
All nations are happily united and at peace
和平共处
under Roman governance.
鉴于此地发生的问题
One might doubt that,
恐怕无法苟同
considering the troubles you are having here.
没法平息狂热教徒和拿撒勒人?
Unable to quell the zealots and Nazarenes?
我已经把他们都击垮了
I have crushed them all.
哦
Oh.
恕我来迟
I can only apologize.
等这件长袍花了点时间
But I was waiting on this new gown.
很好看
Very nice.
伤感的是 我不得不遣走我一个裁缝
Sadly, I just had to dismiss one of my seamstresses.
你今天遣走了一个仆人?
You dismissed a servant today?
是的
Yes.
你不能饶恕她?
You could not forgive her?
遣走她已然是饶恕
Dismissing her was an act of forgiveness.
为什么? 她做了什么?
Why? What had she done?
她...
Well, she...
她在我这里犯了什么罪行?
What crime has she committed under my roof?
算不上罪行 没什么大不了的
No crime in Roman law. It's nothing.
她要加入那伙拿撒勒人
She was attempting to join the Nazarene cult.
但是我以为你已经击垮他们了
But I thought you had crushed them all.
- 带她过来  - 遵命 巡抚
- Bring her here.  - Yes, governor.
愿神与你同在
God be with you.
你也是
And with you.
我想问问你一个教友的事
I wanted to ask you about one of your brethren.
一个大数人叫扫罗的
A man called Saul of Tarsus.
他怎么了?
What of him?
他树了几个敌
He has made some enemies.
他就是有这个本事
It's a special skill of his.
我们已经开始注意他了
He has been brought to our attention.
我要你帮个忙
I need a favor from you.
跟扫罗有关?
To do with Saul?
我要你带他来找我们
I want you to bring him to us.
然后呢?
And then?
然后就跟你没关系了
That is not your concern.
但我们都是信仰基督的兄弟
But he's my brother in Christ.
你要考虑的是对我的忠诚
All you need to think of are your loyalties
还有你许下的承诺
and the promises you have made
仅此而已
to me.
我不能 没有...
I can't. There is no...
想想神殿
Think of the temple.
发发慈悲吧 她们只是女人... 仆人
For pity's sake. They're women... servants.
她们在我的家里密谋投敌
They have committed treason under my roof.
这远称不上是投敌
It's hardly treason.
她们让我颜面扫地
They have humiliated me.
我要人当众鞭打她们
They will be flogged in public
如此才能让从罗马到埃塞俄比亚举国皆知
so the whole world from Rome to Ethiopia shall know.
你真的觉得大帝会关心
Do you really think the emperor will care
如此俗务吗?
about something as tawdry as this?
希望他会
Let's hope he does.
哥尼流
Cornelius.
押她们到客人那
Escort them to our dear guests.
哪一个应该先受刑?
Which one should I flog first?
不要怕
Don't be afraid.
耶稣会给你力量
Jesus will give you strength.
她 只有她
Her. Just her.
我对你另有安排
I have something else planned for you.
希律 你把叛乱分子带到我的宫殿
You have brought insurgents into my palace, Herod.
我豪不知情
I had no idea.
你当赞同下面的惩罚
You will show approval for these actions.
你当敬仰罗马帝国的权威
You will admire the power of Rome.
而当这一切结束
And then when this is over,
你当带着妻子离开我的宫殿
you will take your wife and get out of my palace.
明白吗?
Do you understand?
如你所愿
As you wish.
抱歉让你目睹这一切
I'm sorry you have to witness this.
所有罗马的敌人都会受到惩罚以及镇压
All enemies of Rome are punished and crushed.
无一幸免
None are spared.
为了帝国的荣耀
For the glory of our emperor.
我觉得不该相信她
I think it's a mistake to trust her.
她只是个罗马婊子
She's no more than a Roman whore.
她有影响力
She has influence.
一有机会她就会背叛我们
She will betray us at the first opportunity.
我知道她一定会
I know she will.
也许吧 但那也是我们要承担的风险
Possibly, but that's a risk we have to take.
伊娃 这是我们唯一的机会
We have this one chance, Eva.
把我们的城市从罗马的暴政中拯救出来
One glorious opportunity to free our city from Roman rule.
- 那个雕像...  - 我知道
- That statue...  - I know.
对不起 但我们要杀的是一个
I'm sorry, but we are murdering a man
没有罪过也无冒犯的人
who has not sinned or caused offense.
他都不是罗马人
He is no Roman.
在我看来只是有些大嘴巴
Just a loudmouth, as far as I can tell.
我得走了
I have to go.
你怎么不去听听这个人传教?
Why don't you go and listen to this man preach?
看看他是不是真如利亚说的那样糟
See if he really is as bad as Leah makes him out to be.
你好
Shalom.
你不能那么做
You can't do that.
她们不过是女仆
They were housemaids.
你不能像那样跟我争执
You can't argue with me like that,
也不能当众反对我
and you can't show your disapproval in public.
我没说话
I didn't say word.
你的脸说明一切
Your face.
好吧 如果我的表现不像你想的
Well, I'm sorry if my performance
那样完美 我向你道歉
wasn't as polished as you might have liked.
不要有下次
Don't do it again.
另一个会怎样?
What will happen to the other one?
我不知道
I don't know.
还没想好怎样才更有价值
I haven't worked out how to make it count.
什么更有价值?
Make what count?
她的死
Her death.
约亚拿!
Joanna!
我的爱人
My love.
不要哭
Don't cry.
我现在很平静
I am at peace.
现在没什么能伤害我
Nothing can hurt me now.
你是最棒的丈夫
You were the best husband.
为我们有过的一切感到幸福吧
So be happy for what we had.
你们所有人都会重生...
You can all be born again...
与神修好 从神殿的专制中解放
Reconciled with God, freed from the temple's tyranny.
有一种新的生活 新的自由
There is a new life, a new freedom,
从耶稣基督的爱中来
and it comes from the love of Jesus Christ.
不要害怕他的话语
You must not be afraid of his message.
耶稣并不是来废除律法的 而是来完全律法
Jesus came not to abolish the law, but to fulfill it.
所有我们之前学到的
All that we have been taught before
引导我们来到这一刻
has led us to this very moment.
你怎么看?
What did you think?
现在 现在 就是现在...
Now, now, now is the time...
这是你们的异教所信仰的吗?
Is this what your cult believes?
一部分吧
Some of it.
他说的那些话会毁掉你们的新教会
He will destroy your new church with those words.
我跟利未说就让他去吧
I told Levi we should leave him alone,
专心我们自己的事情就好
concentrate on our own affairs.
但现在不行了
But not now.
他不能这么威胁神殿
He can't threaten the temple like that.
他死了对我们都有好处
It would help us all if he were gone.
日落时把扫罗单独带到客栈
Deliver Saul alone to the inn at sunset.
赎罪日一结束我们就完成剩下的事
Once Yom Kippur has finished, we'll do the rest.
你现在是我们这边的
You are with us now.
是我这边的
You are with me.
对吗?
Yes?
对不起
I'm sorry.
非常 非常抱歉
I'm so, so sorry.
挨打的该是我
It should have been me.
没错
Yes, it should.
你知道事情会这样
You knew what would happen.
这全是我一个人的错
The fault is mine alone.
这里是给她的一些钱和草药
Here is some money and herbs and medicine for her.
你有去处吗?
Do you have somewhere you can go?
有
Yes.
巡抚正忙着处理政务
The governor is busy with affairs of state.
如果你现在走 他就见不到你
If you go now, he will not see you.
也不会知道我参与其中
And he will not know of my involvement in this.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我还能怎么做呢?
What else could I do?
约亚拿怎么办?
And what of Joanna?
走吧
Go now.
祝你安好
I wish you well.
发生什么事了?
What's happened?
请你别哭
Please don't cry.
因为如果神与我们同在 谁能与我们对抗?
Because if God is with us, who can be against us?
而神就与你同在 大比大
And God is with you, Tabitha.
任何事都不能把你
Nothing can separate you
和基督的爱分离... 任何事
from the love of Christ... Nothing.
生不能 死不能 天使抑或恶魔都不能
Not life, not death, nor angels or demons.
人不能 权柄不能
No one, no power.
没有任何权力能把我们同主的爱分开
No authority can separate us from the love of God.
而那爱就是耶稣基督
And that love is Jesus Christ.
是彼拉多下令打她的
She was beaten on Pilate's orders.
我得告诉你一件事
I need to tell you something.
我把整个民族的罪都放在山羊之上
I lay all of nation's sins upon this goat.
让他逃回荒野
Let him escape into the wilderness
带走我们所有的罪!
and take all our sins away!
走吧!
Away!
对不起 我不是恨扫罗
I'm so sorry. I don't hate Saul.
不是这样的
It's not like that.
我只是想保护神殿
I just wanted to protect the temple.
你动摇了 但还没走远
You slipped, but not that far.
所以我们该怎么做?
So, what do we do?
那些狂热信徒知道他在哪吗?
Do the zealots know where he's staying?
那他暂时安全
Then he's safe here for now.
不 这可不一定
No. We don't know that.
他... 他对自己是种危险
He is a... a danger to himself,
所以他对我们也是危险
and therefore he is a danger to us.
我们对耶稣的信仰本身就危险
Our belief in Jesus is the danger.
不 该亚法愿与我们和平共处后就不是了
No. Not now that Caiaphas has offered us peace.
我认为扫罗才是问题所在
I think that Saul is the problem.
他的观点太激进了 会让我们分崩离析
His views are too radical. They will pull us apart.
西门的举动就是证明
Simon's actions are proof of this.
你误解了他的热情
You misunderstand his passion.
我们知道大祭司对他的看法
We know how the High Priest feels about him.
他告诉我的 现在又有狂热信徒这事
He told me so. And the zealots.
他被赶出了大马士革
He was chased out of Damascus.
他是拿我们所有人的命在冒险
He risks all of our lives.
所以你想怎么样?
So what do you suggest?
他们让你怎么做?
What did they tell you to do?
等赎罪日结束我得带他到
I have to take him to an inn in the lower city
下城的一家客栈
as soon as Yom Kippur ends.
好 所以我们日落前还有时间
Right, so we have till the end of the day.
做什么? 他是我们的一员
To do what? He's one of us.
你到底在计划什么?
So what on earth are you planning?
西门回来了 所以很明显
Simon's back, which obviously means
你们都在谈论我的事情
you're all talking about me.
祝你成功
We wish you every success.
- 啊  - 我听说腓力
- Ah.  - I hear Philip has made
在撒玛利亚有了大进展
some great progress in Samaria.
我在耶路撒冷能做得更好
I could do better right here in Jerusalem.
我认为你在耶路撒冷之外
I think there's a bigger role for you
能有更大作为 扫罗
beyond Jerusalem, Saul.
有人要你的命
Men want you dead.
哦 我不怕死 雅各
Oh, I'm not afraid of death, James.
我努力想把你们向前拉
I'm trying to drag you all forward,
但没有人... 没有人愿意听
and no one... no one will listen.
那样不安全
It's not safe.
而你留下 我们会为你担惊受怕
And we're scared for you if you stay here.
仅此而已
That is all.
我懂了
I see.
所以.. 我们还是兄弟了?
So... we are all still brothers, then?
- 当然  - 啊
- Of course.  - Ah.
我们还会再见?
And we will meet again?
我保证
I promise.
那好吧
Well, then.
我不该再拿你们的生命冒险了
I shall risk your lives no longer.
我现在就走 一路上宣扬他的言语
I will leave now, teach his message as I go.
是的 到大数之时
Yes, by the time I get to Tarsus,
我会有一百位追随者
I will have a hundred followers.
你会比我们所有人成就的更大
You will do more than any of us.
神与你们所有人同在
God be with you all.
如果耶路撒冷待不下去了 欢迎来找我
If Jerusalem gets too much, you're always welcome.
包括你 西门
Even you, Simon.
一切在此结束
This ends here.
最终两集
拯救这座城市免于罗马屠杀
Save the city from Roman massacre.
是否同仇敌忾?
Are you with us?
叛乱者奋起
预言将完成
你敢相信吗?
Do you dare to believe?
我相信
I believe.